<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons why the House of Commons ought in justice forthwith to suspend the members charged by the army, from sitting in the house, and to proceed in judgment against them. Or else the city is obliged by way of requitall to help the army to justice upon them.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E396_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201639</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862138</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862138</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160339</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92295)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E396[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons why the House of Commons ought in justice forthwith to suspend the members charged by the army, from sitting in the house, and to proceed in judgment against them. Or else the city is obliged by way of requitall to help the army to justice upon them.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Expulsion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160339:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASONS why the Houſe of Commons ought In Juſtice forthwith to ſuſpend the MEMBERS <hi>Charged by the Army, from ſitting in the Houſe,</hi> And to proceed in Judgment againſt them. Or elſe the City is obliged by way of requitall to help the ARMY to juſtice upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:160339:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:160339:2"/>
            <head>REASONS why the Houſe of Commons ought In Juſtice forthwith to ſuſpend the Members charged by the Army, from ſitting in the Houſe, and to proceed in Judgement againſt them, Or elſe the City is obliged by way of requitall to help the <hi>Army</hi> to Juſtice upon them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Herein to ſpeak with all due Reverence to the Honorable Houſe, the queſtion rightly ſtated will be thus; Whether it be any breach of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg to require ſuch a preſent ſuſpention for ſuch reaſons and matters which are already fully known to the Houſe, having been acted in the Houſe, or there examined and fully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? Or whether thoſe other high miſdemeanors charged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them ought firſt to be proved, which will require ſome time, and I conceive that there ought to be an immediate and preſent <hi>Sequeſtration</hi> of their perſons from that great Counſel; and that I may make forth this truth for the ſatisfaction of the intelligent Reader, in point of rational conviction, grounded upon the Laws of this Kingdom; I ſhal premiſe a few <hi>Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:160339:3"/>and argue the point as in quiet times upon the Law of the Land, which is the only rule of juſtice in times of peace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it hath ever been the courſe of all <hi>arbitrary Courts,</hi> not to ſuffer their priviledges to be queſtioned, nor to be known to any, but to themſelves; that ſo when they are minded to oppreſs any Clyent, if they be <hi>non-pluſt</hi> in point of reaſon, they may fly to the courſe of the <hi>Court,</hi> and ſay it is but the priviledg of the <hi>Court,</hi> as King <hi>James</hi> in his ſpeech in the <hi>Star-chamber</hi> ſaies that the priviledges of that <hi>Court</hi> were ſo tranſcendent that they were not to be diſputed by common Lawyers, and charged the <hi>Chancellor</hi> to check the preſumptuous boldneſs of ſuch Lawyers as durſt argue and diſpute of the limits and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and the decapitated <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> in the high Commiſſion <hi>Court</hi> made an expreſs Inhibition that no <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſter</hi> ſhould preach of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> and matters of ſuch high concernment; and formerly in the <hi>Court of Wards,</hi> he that argued for the King, to finda <hi>Tonure</hi> to fetter and clog the ſubjects Lands, could never want a reaſon; for if neither Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law; nor Statute law, not Cuſtom, not the Kings <hi>Prc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogativo</hi> could carry it, then it was the priviledg of the <hi>Coure</hi> ſo to do; that if the Counſel ſhould ſay, give my Client what is his due by the Common Law, then ſayes the Court give us what is our due by the priviledg of the <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Honor and Rites</hi> whereof we ſit here to maintain; and upon that ground the Papiſts made <hi>marriage a Sacrament,</hi> that if <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould ſay give me my due, <hi>marriage</hi> belongs to the Civil <hi>Magiſtrate;</hi> the <hi>Anſwer</hi> is, give God his due, <hi>Sacraments</hi> belong to the <hi>Church;</hi> and ſo it was in our <hi>Spiritual</hi> (or rather <hi>Carnal</hi>) <hi>Courts,</hi> when the unreaſonableneſs of Excommunication for trifles was objected, oh tis' the priviledg of the <hi>Court</hi> ſo to do.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God the ſubject is well infranchiſed in theſe <hi>Particulars,</hi> and yet King <hi>Charls</hi> muſt have his due, the <hi>Army</hi> have declared their deſires therein, and his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſaies he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires no more, and certainly he deſerves no leſs: I cannot but obſerve what plotting there is to make the Kings late party be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> diſlikes the <hi>Armies</hi> proceedings; one <hi>B. Rheymes</hi> informing the <hi>Right Honorable</hi> the Houſe of <hi>Peers</hi> thereof; a Relation was printed by <hi>Order,</hi> as was but juſt for every <hi>Court</hi> gives indubitate credence to informations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:160339:3"/>the contrary appear, or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to conſider of the improbability of it; that the King ſhould deſire private conference with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtronger (for the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was never any <hi>Courtier</hi> nor ſo much as known to the King) is very ſtrange to me, and the Relation indeed is repugnant in it ſelf, for my own part I think it is ſomething like the <hi>Romiſh Tranſlation,</hi> and not a word of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> true, for I find the <hi>Areny</hi> expreſſing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and where his <hi>Majeſties</hi> beſt intereſt and hopes lie, I refer the <hi>Reader</hi> to the <hi>Kingdoms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> lately printed, with this, that King <hi>Charls</hi> ſhal be King of <hi>Pree men</hi> governing according to juſt and whole ſome Laws, by which to command one man is more honorable in the Judgment of men that are truly ſo, then to have abſolute power of life and death over ten thouſand Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley ſlaves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning the <hi>Pavliament priviledges,</hi> there are very few Caſes printed in any Law books, the Houſes have always been the proper Judges of their own <hi>Proviledges:</hi> the <hi>Journal</hi> books and books of <hi>Remembrances</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> in both Houſes being matters of <hi>Record</hi> and <hi>Regiſters</hi> of their Priviledges and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and when a ſpecial caſe happen for which there is no <hi>Preſident</hi> then right Reaſon muſt be judg.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Honerable Houſe of Commons,</hi> the <hi>repreſenvdtive</hi> body of the Kingdom, the priviledges of that Houſe are great, for <hi>Parliament are muſt</hi> being the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; the <hi>Truſtees</hi> muſt have <hi>inſwrabld Priviledges;</hi> now a <hi>Priviledg</hi> is <hi>private <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> an Exemption from ſome general Law for the eaſe and benefit of the priviledged party, and a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Law muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as well as a publick Law, but the <hi>power</hi> of the Houſe is far above the <hi>priviledg</hi> of the Houſe, they being impowered for the common good; and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves priviledged for the better carrying on of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The firſt day of <hi>Parliament</hi> M. <hi>Speaker</hi> in his ſpeech to the King alwayes concludes with a <hi>prayer</hi> in the name of the Houſe that they may enjoy their ancient and undoubted <hi>priviledges,</hi> the eſſentials whereof are Three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>freedom from Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for themſelves their neceſſary ſervants.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Freedom</hi> of debate, the very life of Counſels</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they may not be drawn <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:160339:4"/>by themſelves, unleſs for <hi>Treaſons</hi> or <hi>Felonies,</hi> which are appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently ſo, as if a <hi>Member</hi> ſhould kill a man there is no queſtion but he ought to be tryed by the Common Law, which is the common <hi>arbiter</hi> of life and death.</p>
            <p>This being laid as a <hi>ſubſtratum</hi> and <hi>ground-work,</hi> I conceive thereby that if any conſiderable number of men, free from all faction and conſpiracy, ſhal by Petition or Remonſtrance, which is an humble way, make a complaint to the Houſe of Ten or Twenty of the <hi>Members,</hi> charging them with high miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and amongſt the reſt that they by <hi>artiſicial practiſes</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Houſe and poyſon the very fountain of Juſtice, that they cauſe diviſions between the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and ſuch men as have given moſt large teſtimonies of their <hi>cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al affections</hi> to the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and are ready to aver and make good their <hi>Charge,</hi> praying that the parties may be ſuſpended from voting in the Houſe for the <hi>preſent;</hi> this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition ought to be granted for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the ſuſpenſion is but in <hi>order</hi> to the <hi>tryal;</hi> A Petition to the Houſe is equivalent to an <hi>original writ;</hi> upon every acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or accuſation ſomething by the Law muſt be done in <hi>order</hi> to the <hi>tryal:</hi> a man is <hi>arreſted</hi> for money, poſſibly there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing due; yet bail muſt be given or the party impriſoned before the <hi>right</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> appears: If the <hi>Charge</hi> be for <hi>treaſon</hi> the party is not bailable, the puniſhment is ſo hainous, unleſs in ſome ſpecial caſe, or that malice is evident; if for <hi>felony,</hi> in ſome caſes the Iudges wil take bayl, if the party be not taken in committing the crym; if for other offences and miſdemeanours, the matter, nature, and riſe of the Charge is principally conſiderable; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſomething muſt be done in order to the tryal; As for any bayl or caution to anſwer the Charge it is <hi>improper,</hi> but the firſt thing <hi>properly</hi> to be don is ſuſpenſion from the Houſ, that they may do no more hurt in the Houſe, and this is but in the nature of an Injunction to prevent further miſcheif; which is granted in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Courts of Iuſtice, upon a bare ſuggeſtion that a man hath Committed waſte and ſpoyl upon the ground before the title be tryed, an injunction is granted to ſtay any further waſtes. The writ called <hi>de leproſo amovendo,</hi> to remove a Leper is granted upon a bare ſuggeſtion, before it be tryed, whether the party be a <hi>Laper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> not, that the healths of others may not be indangered.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:160339:4"/>
2. This can be no prejudice to the Members, for if the Honſt pleaſe to hear the proofs, the matter may be ended in a ſhort time; but if they ſit there, it cannot be imagined (whatſoever they may pretend) that they deſire a ſpeedy tryal, if the Houſe pleaſe to ſuſpend them, but for a moneth, and hear the proofs in that time, what prejudice can it be in right reaſon? The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of every Charge where no malice is apparent, is preſumed to be true, and that's the reaſon that the Law favours the Plaintiff, preſuming the cauſe of Action to be juſt; for though the moſt confident Accuſation, is not the leaſt proof to condemn, for then none ſhould be Innocent, yet tis a violent preſumption that t'is true, and the party to be ſeoured, for the Law ſays that a Common fame that ſaith a man is guilty of felony is ſufficient cauſe for a Juſtice of peace to Reſtrain a mans Liberty, a thing in law moſt precious. Now no malice can be preſumed in the <hi>Army</hi> towards the Members ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, they which have ventured their lives for the Parliament and Kingdom, can be ſuppoſed to intend nothing but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good. what they do is for the pure love of Juſtice, they and the whole Kingdom deſire peaee, and ſpeedy Juſtice; which only can cure the Conſumption of this Kingdom; theſe are the principal obſtructers of Juſtice, and hinderers of poor <hi>Irelands</hi> releif, and theſe men to accompliſh their ambitious ends, ſtudy to imbroyl this poor Kingdom in a ſecond and more bloody war; and care not to ſet all on fire; ſo as they may <hi>Nere</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like warm themſelves: and ſo great is their influence in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Houſe, that ſo long as they ſit there, no Reformation can be expected, and therefore they ought to be ſuſpended.</p>
            <p>But it may be demanded,<note place="margin">Object.</note> why may not theſe men ſit in the Houſe and vote in other matters, till the whole Charge be proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them?</p>
            <p>By no means for ſo the matter wil be endleſs, men that have cunning wits wil drive every Vote to their own ends:<note place="margin">Reſpon.</note> when the Houſe or Committee ſhould ſit to hear the complants againſt them, they ſhal procure an order to put it off for ten days, or bring on other buſineſſes, and pretend abſence of witneſſes; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, as upon every Summons at Law there are fifteen days given, ſo is it in Committees, Tediens protractions, and dangerous delays, which the Condition of the <hi>Army</hi> cannot admit, to go
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:160339:5"/>a Circular courſe of Law againſt them, by way of Bil, Anſwer, and Replication; but if they were not guilty of the matters Charged againſt them they would not fear being ſuſpended: ſome of them can be out of the Houſe moneths together, for their own eaſe or profit, why ſhould not the Houſe do right to the <hi>Army</hi> in this particular?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obs.</hi> But muſt not the Houſe preſerve it ſelf? if Ten Members may be ſuſpended in this manner, why not as wel Twenty or a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and ſo the whol Houſe might be diſſolved, and ſo a failer of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> No ſuchmatter, every Court hath an intrinſecal power, by the Rules of Law to conſerve it ſelf: if the cheif Juſtice of the Kings bench or common Pleas be liable to any action, the writ may be taken out againſt him in the name of the <hi>Secondary</hi> Judgs and ſo againſt Three Judges, in the name of the Fourth. But if the four Iudges be all bound in one bound joyntly, this Bond cannot be ſued againſt them all in this Court, for then there would be a failer of Iuſtice; they may not be Iudges in their own caſe, but one or two of the Iudges may be ſued in their own Court, and they are to be Removed from off the bench, and ſit below amongſt the officers of the Court, uncovered; and therefore one of the Iudges, in the <hi>Queens</hi> time, being ſued in an action of Debt, becauſe he might not ſit in the Court while the Action againſt him was depending, by conſent came to a ſpeedy tryal, and the matter was ended in a day or two; what a happy thing would it be for this Kingdom, if every mans cauſe might be ended ſo ſoon, or at leaſt in a moneth or two, the Lord grant it may be ſo.</p>
            <p>But out the caſe, that there was a Law that no Member of the Houſe of Commons ſhould be ſuſpended, nor accuſed, but by the Oathes of Twenty witneſſes, as the Cardinals are not to be Impeached but by Twenty Accuſers, ſhal an Army of ſuch gallant faithful men that have been Inſtruments to ſave the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, be ſubject to a dead Letter? the Kingdom now intreats them to ſee Iuſtine done, ſhal the Houſes to gratify thoſe few Incendiaries indanger the ruin of the whole Kingdom? or ſhal the <hi>Army</hi> to preſerve an unneceſſary priviledg, neglect to ſee the Comon Rights, and Libertys of the people ſetled, which they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:160339:5"/>have fought for all this while? muſt we to prevent a ſmall inconvenience enforce a greater? there is no previledge of the Houſe of Commons that muſt ſtand in competition with the ſafety of the people: the Law is Lord of particular caſes and perſons, but the univerſall good is Lord over it: what Law was there to reſtrain any man from going between Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford and London, but the ſafety of the people? and what ſchiſme is it in the body, to pull out an aking tooth, though ſeated in the head? This is a farre ſtronger caſe then <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords</hi> or <hi>Canterburies,</hi> who yet lay long in priſon before they were tried: the Armie are ſo farre from the leaſt face of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, that though theſe men have voted them enemies to the State, for that which the Parliament ſince acknowledge to be juſt, that they do not ſo much as deſire to have them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, which in juſtice they might well expect, but they deſire onely their abſence from the Houſe, that their hands and tongues may be tied from doing further hurt to the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>If the caſe of the five Members ſhould be objected, there is no compariſon between them; for the King cannot accuſe any ſubject; and they were demanded in a hoſtile manner, becauſe they voted for the liberty of the people; but theſe Members of late have voted nothing in the Houſe, but meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſlave the people: he that was one of the five, is as a ſtar fallen from heaven, which was no ſtarre, but a Comet: 'tis pitty good parts ſhould be imployed to make ſlaves of thoſe that intruſted them.</p>
            <p>But ſtill it will be ſaid, can words make any man guilty? I anſwer, their actions clearely beſpeake their intentions, which is the ruine of this Army, to diſgrace and oppreſſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that will not conforme to their practiſes, but ſtands in the way of their Domination, to Lord it over the Lords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; all their Votes tend to inſlave them whom they ſhould enfranchiſe; and it is moſt apparent that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intend to doe right to the King nor the people: This is ſufficiently knowne to the Houſe, that theſe were the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall actors in procuring that haſtie Declaration againſt this Army, which is the wonderment of Heathens, that men who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:160339:6"/>with the venture of their lives had vindicated the Petitions of Right, ſhould be denied the right and Liberty to preſent their grievances to their noble Generall, and this Declaration to be paſt in the Houſe late in the night, contrary to Order of the Houſe, that it ſhould not be debated till the next day, when the Armies friends were gone away, and ſo the Houſe ſurprized, and abuſed; and theſe are the men that afterwards of their owne accord, without any warrant from the Houſe, called back thoſe three Regiments out of Worceſter-ſhire, that were going for the relefe of Ireland, and what plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there was between ſome of theſe Members, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formadoes, abetting them to come downe to the Houſe, and impriſon the Members in the Houſe till ſome of them by their elegant ſpeeches pacified them; and what high affronts have been and are daily offered to thoſe that are the Armies friends, let but everie reaſonable man ſeriouſly conſider, Whether the Houſe in juſtice has not ſufficient clear ground to ſuſpend theſe men from any longer ſitting, til the other heads of the Charge be cleerly united; which if it be denied, if the Army cannot finde juſtice from the Houſe in the Hundred, how ſhal they expect it in the Shire? If theſe men have ſuch an influence and power in the Houſe, that they may not be ſuſpended in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a triall, what hopes has the Army, that the Houſe ſhould inflict condigne puniſhment upon them according to their demerits, though I believe the Army deſires they ſhould be more mercifully dealt withall then they intended towards the Army, had they been disbanded?</p>
            <p>If one ſtrike a man in Weſtminſter-Hall, in the face of the Court, he ſhall loſe his hand without any further proof; and if the Court adjudge an Infant of ſixteen to be of full age, by inſpection, there is no averment againſt it; now not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Houſe, but every man that walkes in Weſtminſter-Hall, knowes that theſe men are the principall firebrands in the Houſe.</p>
            <p>But come you worthy Citizens, what if the honourable Houſe of Commons will not doe juſtice upon them, for my part I know no other way to the ſafety of this Kingdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the preſent ſuſpending of theſe Members; for as ſure
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:160339:6"/>as the Lord is in heaven, if they continue in the Houſe, they will imbroyle this Kingdome in a new warre, by private liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, inviting the Scots, or rather then faile, to make a peace with the Iriſh Rebells, and bring them over, calumniating the Army, or otherwiſe, what will you doe in this caſe? pray let me give you counſell without a fee; if it taſte bitter, as I hope it will not, to any found palate, ſwallow it downe, for it is wholſome; doe not I beſeech you (upon any pretences) raiſe any Forces againſt this Army; do not alledge you muſt defend the City, of whom are you afraid? Is not the Army the beſt friend that ever the City had, have they not been your ſtrongeſt walls and Bulwarks? will you be briars and thorns to them? had not your enemies long ſince deflowred your Virgin City, had not they ſtood in the gap? Rejoyce rather, never ſuch true cauſe of ringing the bells, and making bonefires, gallant Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and his Army, under God, preſervers of your City, is coming; now keep holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and write over your dooers, <hi>Victoria:</hi> this is the ſecond nativity of London, every thing ſhall be ſetled for the good of us, and this Kingdome, as well as heart can wiſh; let's give them our beſt wine to drinke, that have ventured their lives for us; truly 'tis but juſtice ſo to doe; 'tis no charity to relieve that poore man that has ſaved my life; all the wealth in the City is not ſufficient to requite this Army: But mee thinks I heare a poore honeſt heart ſay, this would doe well, if there were not a difference between the Parliament and Army; good friend doe not miſtake, the Charge is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, but ſome corrupt wormes in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that are to be purged out, that the Body Politique may be the ſounder: but what if we be commanded to our Armes? Oh conſider what you doe, and aske counſell from heaven! a warre is quickly begun but not eaſily ended, the firſt blow is like leaping into a deep pit, or as opening the floud-gates; if there ſhould be a breach between Parliament and Army, which God forbid, who made it? who gives the firſt blow? what had the Army done to be declared enemies, for preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Petition to the noble Generall, which (by the Law of Armes, all ſouldiers have liberty to do) in caſe they ſhould
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:160339:7"/>perſiſt in it? which ſince the Parliament has acknowledged to be but juſt; and though that Declaration be ſince retracted, the unbending of the bow does not heale the hurt made by the arrow; when the wound is cured (though I thinke all ſober men counted it at the beſt, but an impolitike and haſty Declaration, full of ingratitude; to ſay no more of it) yet the ſcar remaines ſo farre, as that it was a ſufficient Declaration how the chiefe promoters of it intended to deale with the Army when disbanded, Rebels, Traitors Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, and Schiſmaticks, men not worthy to have a mouthfull of ayre in the Kingdome, though under God they had ſaved it; but when by their meanes a bleſſed Reformation (for the good of this poore Kingdome) ſhall be effected, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and common honeſtie ſhall be highly exalted; how will the world then ſtand and admire, and ſay with <hi>David, mirabilis Deus in ſanctis ſuis,</hi> God is greatly to be admired in his Saints. Doe but conſider ſeriouſly of it, for which of the Armies good works at Naesby, Briſtow <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt they in all haſte be ſtoned? Weigh their proceedings in an equall ballance, ſince the Charge ſent up againſt the eleven Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, they have kept at a diſtance, expecting juſtice to be done upon them, it cannot be obtained; they approach the City for that purpoſe onely: Oh bid them welcome, the ſword is but the ſervant of juſtice, and ſervants of juſtice are the Kingdomes beſt friends; take heed you do them no wrong, my life on it they will do you none; you know they are no cowards, when their cauſe is good, the juſtice of heaven is for them, they have aſſiſted you againſt thoſe who had deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ruine of your famous City: It is but juſtice and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon equity, that you ſhould aſſiſt them againſt thoſe that had deſigned theirs, and in them the ruine of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for believe it, under the ſpecious pretences of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, order, and uniformity, the deſigne of theſe men and their Accomplices, was no other but to get the Kings power into their own hands, to monopolize all the great places to themſelves and their Adherents, to continue Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of Parliament during their lives, and to make us the moſt abſolute ſlaves that ever were in this Kingdome, both for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:160339:7"/>ſoules, bodies, and eſtates: conſider further, what can you get by oppoſing this Army, for though the Commanders and Officers be not Souldiers of fortune, but Gentlemen of worth and quality, and few of the ſouldiery but know how to live comfortably; for you ſee it is not money they aime at, being acted by more noble principles, the love of juſtice, and vertue, for which they firſt ingaged, yet if they find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, nature juſtifies ſelfe-defence, and juſtice muſt be done; you may loſe much, and in the loſſe of this Army, you and yours are likely to be inſlaved for ever, you know God has owned this Army as thoſe that are holy, faithfull, and choſen, and all Counties where they come owne them and love them, and feare nothing but their disbanding before the peace of this Kingdome be ſetled, and the Liberties of the Subject vindicated: pray read the 8. of <hi>Numbers, the Lord is with them, and the ſhout of a King is amongſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore as you love this Kingdome, make not the leaſt head, nor face of reſiſtance againſt them; you and they are as two veſſels at ſea, if you claſh upon one another, you are broken: he that gives the firſt blow ingages the Juſtice of Heaven againſt him, ſet open your gates, if you have no inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine troublers, you may throw down your works; the Army under God, will be your ſufficient defence: doe not object that to require juſtice in this manner is to enforce the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, force and right are oppoſed; force being properly of things unlawful, 'tis no force to make a man to be honeſt; theſe Members accuſed, might have acted and voted freely for the infranchiſement of the people, but they are not free to vote for our inſlavement; tis a common Argument, that by this meanes the Houſes are over-awed, and not in a free capacity; but it beares not the weight of a feather: For;</p>
            <p n="1">1. God, and nature, law, and reaſon all command the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of juſtice, and hee that ordaines the end, alwayes appoints ſome means or other conducing to that end: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when the Liberty of a people cannot be ſetled but by a defenſive war, that muſt needs be lawfull: but this is the caſe, there happens an unhappy difference betweene the Houſes, and the Army, the Parliament ſay, they will make the Kingdome happy; the Army fears it, and ſayes it will not bee done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:160339:8"/>theſe Incendiaries bee removed: Now the Queſtion is, Whether the Army ought not in Law and conſcience to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in armes till this difference be ended, and there is nothing more cleare, then that they ought; for it is a rule in Law, and univerſall reaſon, that when a ſuit is begun all things muſt reſt as they then are till the matter be ended and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged, for to deliver up the ſword, is to releaſe the right.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is no force unlawfully raiſed, but commiſſionated by the Parliament for the freedome of themſelves, and the whole Kindome, not to fight with an implicite faith, but for juſtice, and common Liberties, and properties; and there can no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument bee uſed againſt the Army, for whetting their gliſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſwords, againſt the injuſtice of theſe men, and keeping them unſheathed untill the King and Kingdome bee ſetled in Honour, and ſafty, but what may bee improved againſt the Parliament, for the firſt raiſeing of this Army?</p>
            <p>Let not theſe and ſuch like Incendiaryes, nor their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices in pulpits nor elſewhere, abuſe you into any prejudices or jealouſies, as that the Army was raiſed and paid by the Parliament, and that the ſervants oppoſe their Maſters; juſt as the Biſhops argued, wee are the ſhepheards, ye are the ſheepe, ſhall the ſheepe oppoſe the ſhepheards? tis the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that payes the Army, and they contribute thereunto out of their owne eſtates, but the Parliament are ſo wiſe in all their declarations, to exempt themſelves from payments; the Army fight for themſelves, and for the good of the Kingdome, and are true to their firſt principles, Iuſtice and Lawfull Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for the love whereof they will adventure ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand lives a peece, if they had them: For my part, if they ſhould willingly disband, before our Liberties be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſecured, I ſhould proclaime it to all the world, that they had betrayed us. Have honeſt men laid out themſelves to their very ſhirts, and muſt they now be trampled upon, and made at the beſt hewers of wood and drawers of water, if ſo much favour may be granted them, to breath in the Land of their nativity? How is juſtice vineger at the beſt, and gall to the moſt? Proteſtants by a new trick made Papiſts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted upon the Statutes of Recuſants, honeſt men impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:160339:8"/>every where, as if it were no more to impriſon a man then to whip a Schoole-boy; Petitions burnt, a thing never heard of amongſt Heathen Magiſtrates, that dries up the fountaine of all reliefe; and theſe perſons are the chiefe incendiaries and promoters of all theſe miſchiefs; theſe are the <hi>Phaetons</hi> that would ſet all on fire before the generall conflagration at the day of judgement; for I have a moſt reverent and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable eſteem of many in both Houſes, who in my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, really and ſincerely, without thoſe unworthy and baſe ends of enriching themſelves upon the ruines of others, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the glory of God, and the good of this Kingdome, but are over-voted and ſilenced, as wheat lies buried amongſt the chaffe.</p>
            <p>Therefore, this being no time to write much; All you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Citizens, go down to the Parliament, and cry <hi>Iustice, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> againſt theſe men; take your Bibles, and mark well the 20. Chapter of the ſecond Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> let theſe <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba's</hi> be but ſuſpended the Houſe and juſtice done upon them, and the Army, if you deſire it, will make an honourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, ſo as they may have moneyes not to be chargeable to the almoſt quite exhauſted Countreys: The Army deſires an account of the many millions of money that have been raiſed for the Kingdomes ſervice: In the name of God, let the Treaſurers, Committee-men, and thoſe that have ſwallowed down the money, vomit it up againe; why ſhould they not? let quick and cheap juſtice be done to rich and poore; I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, the work will be glorious if you hinder it not; if you make any oppoſition againſt this Army, you are undone. Farewell the glory of London-Towne: the Lord give you wiſdome to know your friends from your foes: In this will Gods love be manifeſt to the city: I hope your unthankfull Remonſtrance may be forgotten, becauſe you were at the firſt a Sanctuarie for honeſt men; I truſt God will inſpire you to foreſee and prevent your ruine, which can onely be by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with this Army, for which I ſhall pray and conclude my ſelfe an unfeigned well-wiſher of peace and truth, of the honour of the King, and juſt Rights and Liberties of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Kingdome.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
